<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!--
    Herds & Fisheries - Codex Entry Definitions

    One CodexEntryDef per documented mechanic. Descriptions are deliberately
    qualitative: they describe how the system behaves, not specific balance
    constants (which animals are "basic", costs, etc.), which are configured in
    mod settings and would drift out of date here.

    seeAlso entries may reference base-mod Codex entries (Codex_ResourceProduction,
    Codex_FirstSettlement, Codex_BuildingSlots) - the base mod loads first, so
    those defNames resolve. bannerPath on the category supplies the right-pane
    banner; entries are icon-less (a missing iconPath renders fine).
-->
<Defs>

    <FactionColonies.CodexEntryDef>
        <defName>Codex_AH_Overview</defName>
        <label>Raising Livestock</label>
        <description>With [b]Empire Refactored: Herds &amp; Fisheries[/b], your settlements no longer conjure animals and animal goods out of nothing. The animals resource is now tied to the species a settlement can actually raise — if it can raise none, it produces no animal goods at all, no matter how many workers you assign.

A settlement's [b]herds[/b] — its land livestock — can draw on three sources:

[b] - Stocked breeding pairs[/b] — species you have personally delivered to that settlement and bred. These are local to the settlement that raised them.
[b] - Basic farm animals[/b] — a common set available at every settlement from the start (configurable, and can be switched off).
[b] - Cloned species[/b] — livestock shared across your whole {FACTION_TITLE} by Cloning Labs.

[b]Fisheries[/b] are a separate axis. A settlement on a coast, river, or lakeshore — in a biome where fish actually live — produces fish automatically; its catch is simply whatever those waters hold. Landlocked settlements have no fishery. (Fishing requires the Odyssey DLC.)

The [i]Livestock[/i] tab on a settlement's window lists every species it can raise and which source it came from, what each produces, and which fish — if any — its waters yield.</description>
        <category>CodexCat_AnimalHusbandry</category>
        <displayOrder>0</displayOrder>
        <iconPath>UI/Banners/Banner-HerdsFisheries</iconPath>
        <seeAlso>
            <li>Codex_AH_Registering</li>
            <li>Codex_AH_CloningLab</li>
            <li>Codex_AH_Fisheries</li>
            <li>Codex_ResourceProduction</li>
        </seeAlso>
    </FactionColonies.CodexEntryDef>

    <FactionColonies.CodexEntryDef>
        <defName>Codex_AH_Registering</defName>
        <label>Stocking Breeding Pairs</label>
        <description>To teach a settlement a new species, bring it there yourself. Form a caravan carrying a breeding pair and travel to the settlement.

A breeding pair is [b]one male and one female[/b]. Animals with no sex instead need any two individuals. A caravan only offers a species for stocking when it can't already be raised there and you are carrying a complete pair.

At the settlement, use the [i]Stock Animals[/i] caravan command — also available by right-clicking the settlement — to choose which species to stock. The pair stays behind to found the herd, and that species is raised there from then on.</description>
        <category>CodexCat_AnimalHusbandry</category>
        <displayOrder>10</displayOrder>
        <seeAlso>
            <li>Codex_AH_Overview</li>
            <li>Codex_FirstSettlement</li>
        </seeAlso>
    </FactionColonies.CodexEntryDef>

    <FactionColonies.CodexEntryDef>
        <defName>Codex_AH_BasicAnimals</defName>
        <label>Basic Farm Animals</label>
        <description>So you are not forced to hand-carry a barnyard to every new settlement, a set of [b]basic farm animals[/b] is available at all settlements from the moment they are founded — no stocking required.

Which species count as "basic", and whether the feature is on at all, are set in the mod settings. The defaults are the familiar farmyard animals. Turn the feature off for a stricter game where [i]every[/i] species must be stocked by sending breeding pairs.</description>
        <category>CodexCat_AnimalHusbandry</category>
        <displayOrder>20</displayOrder>
        <seeAlso>
            <li>Codex_AH_Overview</li>
        </seeAlso>
    </FactionColonies.CodexEntryDef>

    <FactionColonies.CodexEntryDef>
        <defName>Codex_AH_CloningLab</defName>
        <label>The Cloning Lab</label>
        <description>The [b]Cloning Lab[/b] pools livestock across your whole {FACTION_TITLE}. Every species stocked at a settlement that has a Cloning Lab becomes available to [i]all[/i] of your settlements.

Build one at a well-stocked settlement to spread its herd empire-wide; the more species that settlement has stocked, the more every other settlement can raise. It is a higher-tech (Spacer) building, so it arrives as a late-game way to stop managing breeding pairs settlement by settlement and run your livestock from a single hub.</description>
        <category>CodexCat_AnimalHusbandry</category>
        <displayOrder>30</displayOrder>
        <seeAlso>
            <li>Codex_AH_Overview</li>
            <li>Codex_AH_Registering</li>
            <li>Codex_BuildingSlots</li>
        </seeAlso>
    </FactionColonies.CodexEntryDef>

    <FactionColonies.CodexEntryDef>
        <defName>Codex_AH_Fisheries</defName>
        <label>Fisheries</label>
        <description>Where herds must be stocked, [b]fisheries[/b] come from geography. A settlement whose tile touches open water can pull fish from it directly — no breeding pairs, nothing to deliver, no Cloning Lab. If the water is there and the biome has fish, the settlement fishes.

What it can catch depends on the kind of water its tile touches and the fish its biome holds:

[b] - Coastal settlements[/b] land their biome's [i]saltwater[/i] fish.
[b] - River and lakeshore settlements[/b] land its [i]freshwater[/i] fish.

A settlement on both salt and fresh water draws from both. A landlocked tile, or a biome with no fish of its own, has no fishery at all.

Fish are an axis of their own, separate from your herds: a water-adjacent settlement yields its catch even with no livestock stocked. Land animal products still need their breeding pairs — the two systems do not substitute for each other.

This is an Odyssey feature. It can be switched off in the mod settings — turn off [i]restrict fish to water-adjacent settlements[/i] to lift the location requirement, after which fish are treated like any other animal product your settlements raise.

A settlement's [i]Livestock[/i] tab shows what its waters offer, or tells you the tile is landlocked.</description>
        <category>CodexCat_AnimalHusbandry</category>
        <displayOrder>40</displayOrder>
        <seeAlso>
            <li>Codex_AH_Overview</li>
            <li>Codex_ResourceProduction</li>
        </seeAlso>
    </FactionColonies.CodexEntryDef>

</Defs>
